
<?xml-model href="../SchemaDraft.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<speech>
    <meta>
        <name>George W. Bush</name>
        <den>Methodist</den>
        <class>upper</class>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <party>Republican</party>
        <profession>Businessman</profession>
        <term>1</term>
        <title>Address by George W. Bush</title>
        <date>January 20, 2001</date>
    </meta>
    <body>
        <p>Thank you all.</p>
        <p>Chief Justice Rehnquist, President Carter, President Bush—</p>
        <p>President Clinton, distinguished guests, and my fellow citizens:</p>
        <p><tone emotion="pride">This peaceful transfer of authority is rare in history, yet common
                in our country</tone>. With a simple oath, we affirm old traditions and make new
            beginnings.</p>
        <p>As I begin, I thank President Clinton for his service to our Nation.</p>
        <p>And I thank Vice President Gore for a contest conducted with spirit and ended with
            grace.</p>
        <p>I am honored and humbled to stand here, where so many of America’s leaders have come
            before me and so many will follow.</p>
        <p>We have a place, all of us, in a long story; a story we continue, but whose end we will
            not see. It is the story of a new world that became a friend and liberator of the old,
            the story of a <value type="democracy">slave-holding society that became a servant of
                freedom</value>, the story of a power that went into the
                world to protect but not possess, to defend but not to conquer. <tone
                emotion="pride">It is the American story; a story of flawed and fallible people,
                united across the generations by grand and enduring ideals</tone>.</p>
        <p>The grandest of these ideals is an unfolding American promise: <value type="equality"
                >that everyone belongs, that everyone deserves a chance, that no insignificant
                person was ever born</value>.</p>
        <p>Americans are called to enact this promise in our lives and in our laws. And though our
            Nation has sometimes halted, and sometimes delayed, we must follow no other course.</p>
        <p>Through much of the last century, <value type="democracy">America’s faith in freedom and
                democracy was a rock in a raging sea</value>. <policy foreign="internationalism">Now
                it is a seed upon the wind, taking root in many nations</policy>.</p>
        <p><value type="democracy">Our democratic faith is more than the creed of our country, it is
                the inborn hope of our humanity; an ideal we carry but do not own, a trust we bear
                and pass along</value>. <value type="progress">And even after nearly 225 years, we
                have a long way yet to travel</value>.</p>
        <p>While many of our citizens prosper, others doubt the promise—even the justice—of our own
            country. <policy education="schools">The ambitions of some Americans are limited by failing
                schools</policy>, <value type="equality">and hidden prejudice, and the circumstances
                of their birth</value>. And sometimes our differences run so deep, it seems we share
            a continent, but not a country.</p>
        <p>We do not accept this, and we will not allow it. <value type="unity">Our unity, our
                union, is the serious work of leaders and citizens in every generation</value>. And
            this is my solemn pledge: I will work to build a single nation of justice and
            opportunity.</p>
        <p>
            <tone emotion="optimistic">I know this is within our reach</tone>, <value
                type="religion">because we are guided by a power larger than ourselves who creates
                us equal in His image</value>. </p>
        <p><value type="unity">And we are confident in principles that unite and lead us
                onward</value>.</p>
        <p><value type="unity">America has never been united by blood or birth or soil. We are bound
                by ideals that move us beyond our backgrounds, lift us above our interests, and
                teach us what it means to be citizens</value>. Every child
                must be taught these principles. Every citizen must uphold them. <policy
                immigration="pro_immigration">And every immigrant, by embracing these ideals, makes our country
                more, not less, American</policy>.</p>
        <p><value type="civility">Today we affirm a new commitment to live out our Nation’s promise
                through civility, courage, compassion, and character</value>.</p>
        <p><value type="civility">America, at its best, matches a commitment to principle with a
                concern for civility</value>.</p>
        <p><value type="civility">A civil society demands from each of us good will and respect,
                fair dealing and forgiveness</value>.</p>
        <p>Some seem to believe that our politics can afford to be petty because, in a time of
            peace, the stakes of our debates appear small. But the stakes, for America, are never
            small. <policy foreign="internationalism">If our country does not lead the cause of
                freedom, it will not be led</policy>. <tone rhetoric="appeal_to_future">If we do not turn the
                hearts of children toward knowledge and character, we will lose their gifts and
                undermine their idealism</tone>. <policy economy="general">If we permit our economy
                to drift and decline, the vulnerable will suffer most</policy>.</p>
        <p>We must live up to the calling we share. <value type="civility">Civility is not a tactic
                or a sentiment. It is the determined choice of trust over cynicism, of community
                over chaos. And this commitment, if we keep it, is a way to shared
                accomplishment</value>.</p>
        <p>America, at its best, is also courageous.</p>
        <p><tone rhetoric="appeal_to_past">Our national courage has been clear in times of
                depression and war, when defeating common dangers defined our common good. Now we
                must choose if the example of our fathers and mothers will inspire us or condemn
                us</tone>. <tone rhetoric="appeal_to_future">We must show courage in a time of
                blessing by confronting problems instead of passing them onto future
                generations</tone>.</p>
        <p><policy education="schools">Together we will reclaim America’s schools, before ignorance and apathy claim more young lives</policy>. <policy
                health="health_care">We will reform Social Security and Medicare</policy>, <tone
                rhetoric="appeal_to_future">sparing our children from struggles we have the power to
                prevent</tone>. <policy economy="tax">And we will reduce taxes, to recover the
                momentum of our economy and reward the efforts and enterprise of working
                Americans</policy>.</p>
        <p>We will build our defenses beyond challenge, lest weakness invite
                challenge.</p>
        <p><policy military="war">We will confront weapons of mass destruction, so that a new century is
                spared new horrors</policy>.</p>
        <p><value type="democracy">The enemies of liberty and our country should make no
                mistake</value>, <policy foreign="internationalism">America remains engaged in the world,
                by history and by choice, shaping a balance of power that favors freedom. We will
                defend our allies and our interests. We will show purpose without arrogance. We will
                meet aggression and bad faith with resolve and strength. And to all nations, we will
                speak for the values that gave our Nation birth</policy>.</p>
        <p>America, at its best, is compassionate.</p>
        <p>In the quiet of American conscience, we know that <value type="equality">deep, persistent
                poverty is unworthy of our Nation’s promise</value>. <tone
                rhetoric="appeal_to_future">And whatever our views of its cause, we can agree that
                children at risk are not at fault</tone>. <value type="religion">Abandonment and
                abuse are not acts of God; they are failures of love.</value></p>
        <p><policy prison="order">And the proliferation of prisons, however necessary</policy>,
            is no substitute for hope and order in our souls.</p>
        <p>Where there is suffering, there is duty. <value type="equality">Americans in need are not
                strangers, they are citizens; not problems, but priorities</value>. And all of us
            are diminished when any are hopeless.</p>
        <p>Government has great responsibilities, for <value type="security">public safety</value>
            and <policy health="public_health">public health</policy>, <policy civil_rights="civil_rights">for civil
                rights</policy> and <policy education="schools">common schools</policy>. Yet compassion
            is the work of a nation, not just a government. And some needs and hurts are so deep,
            they will only <value type="religion">respond to a mentor’s touch or a pastor’s prayer.
                Church and charity, synagogue and mosque lend our communities their humanity, and
                they will have an honored place in our plans and in our laws</value>.</p>
        <p><value type="equality">Many in our country do not know the pain of poverty. But we can
                listen to those who do</value>. And I can pledge our Nation to a goal. <value
                type="religion">When we see that wounded traveler on the road to Jericho, we will
                not pass to the other side</value>.</p>
        <p>America, at its best, is a place where personal responsibility is valued and
            expected.</p>
        <p>Encouraging responsibility is not a search for scapegoats; it is a call to conscience.
            And though it requires sacrifice, it brings a deeper fulfillment. We find the fullness
            of life, not only in options, but in commitments. And we find that children and
            community are the commitments that set us free.</p>
        <p>Our public interest depends on private character; on civic duty and family bonds and
            basic fairness; on uncounted, unhonored acts of decency which give direction to our
            freedom. <tone emotion="inspiring">Sometimes in life we are called to do great things.
                But as a saint of our times has said, every day we are called to do small things
                with great love. The most important tasks of a democracy are done by
            everyone</tone>.</p>
        <p>I will live and lead by these principles: <value type="civility">to advance my
                convictions with civility</value>; to pursue the public interest with courage; to
            speak for greater justice and compassion; to call for responsibility, and try to live it
            as well. In all these ways, I will bring the values of our history to the care of our
            times.</p>
        <p>What you do is as important as anything government does. I ask you to seek a common good
            beyond your comfort; to defend needed reforms against easy attacks; to serve your
            Nation, beginning with your neighbor. <value type="action">I ask you to be
                citizens—citizens, not spectators; citizens, not subjects; responsible citizens
                building communities of service and a nation of character</value>.</p>
        <p><tone emotion="pride">Americans are generous and strong and decent, not because we
                believe in ourselves, but because we hold beliefs beyond ourselves</tone>. When this
            spirit of citizenship is missing, no government program can replace it. When this spirit
            is present, no wrong can stand against it.</p>
        <p>
            <tone rhetoric="appeal_to_past">After the Declaration of Independence was signed,
                Virginia statesman John Page wrote to Thomas Jefferson:</tone>
        </p>
        <p>We know the race is not to the swift nor the Battle to the Strong. Do you not think an
            Angel rides in the Whirlwind and directs this Storm?</p>
        <p><tone rhetoric="appeal_to_past">Much time has passed since Jefferson arrived for his
                inauguration. The years and changes accumulate, but the themes of this day he would
                know: our Nation’s grand story of courage and its simple dream of dignity</tone>. We
            are not the story’s author, who fills time and eternity with His purpose. His purpose is
            achieved in our duty; and our duty is fulfilled in service to one another.</p>
        <p>Never tiring, never yielding, never finishing, we renew that purpose today: to make our
            country more just and generous; to affirm the dignity of our lives and every life.</p>
        <p>This work continues. This story goes on. And an angel still rides in the whirlwind and
            directs this storm.</p>
        <p>
            <value type="religion">God bless you all, and God bless America</value>. </p>
    </body>
</speech>
