<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../SchemaDraft.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<speech>
    <meta>
        <name>George H.W. Bush</name>
        <den>Episcopal</den>
        <class>upper</class>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <party>Republican</party>
        <profession>Businessman</profession>
        <term>1</term>
        <title>Address by George H.W. Bush</title>
        <date>January 20, 1989</date>
    </meta>



    <body>
        <p>Mr. Chief Justice, Mr. President, Vice President Quayle, Senator Mitchell, Speaker
            Wright, Senator Dole, Congressman Michel, and fellow citizens, neighbors, and
            friends:</p>
        <p>There is a man here who has earned a lasting place in our hearts and in our history.
            President Reagan, on behalf of our Nation, I thank you for the wonderful things that you
            have done for America.</p>
        <p><tone rhetoric="appeal_to_past">I have just repeated word for word the oath taken by
                George Washington 200 years ago</tone>, and <value type="religion">the Bible on
                which I placed my hand is the Bible on which he placed his</value>. <tone
                rhetoric="appeal_to_past">It is right that the memory of Washington be with us
                today, not only because this is our Bicentennial Inauguration, but because
                Washington remains the Father of our Country. And he would, I think, be gladdened by
                this day; for today is the concrete expression of a stunning fact: our continuity
                these 200 years since our government began</tone>.</p>
        <p>We meet on democracy’s front porch, a good place to talk as neighbors and as friends. For
            this is a day when our nation is made whole, when our differences, for a moment, are
            suspended.</p>
        <p><value type="religion">And my first act as President is a prayer. I ask you to bow your
                heads</value>:</p>
        <p>
            <value type="religion">Heavenly Father, we bow our heads and thank You for Your love.
                Accept our thanks for the peace that yields this day and the shared faith that makes
                its continuance likely. Make us strong to do Your work, willing to heed and hear
                Your will, and write on our hearts these words: “Use power to help people.” For we
                are given power not to advance our own purposes, nor to make a great show in the
                world, nor a name. There is but one just use of power, and it is to serve people.
                Help us to remember it, Lord. Amen</value>. </p>
        <p>I come before you and assume the Presidency at a moment rich with promise. <tone
                emotion="optimistic">We live in a peaceful, prosperous time</tone>, but we can make
            it better. <tone emotion="triumph">For a new breeze is blowing, and a world refreshed by
                freedom seems reborn; for in man’s heart, if not in fact, the day of the dictator is
                over</tone>. The totalitarian era is passing, its old ideas blown away like leaves
            from an ancient, lifeless tree. A new breeze is blowing, and a nation refreshed by
            freedom stands ready to push on. There is new ground to be broken, and new action to be
            taken. <value type="action">There are times when the future seems thick as a fog; you
                sit and wait, hoping the mists will lift and reveal the right path. But this is a
                time when the future seems a door you can walk right through into a room called
                tomorrow</value>.</p>
        <p><policy foreign="internationalism">Great nations of the world are moving toward democracy
                through the door to freedom. Men and women of the world move toward free markets
                through the door to prosperity. The people of the world agitate for free expression
                and free thought</policy> through <value type="democracy">the door to the moral and
                intellectual satisfactions that only liberty allows</value>.</p>
        <p><value type="democracy">We know what works: Freedom works. We know what’s right: Freedom
                is right</value>. We know how to secure a more just and prosperous life for man on
            Earth: through free markets, free speech, free elections, and the exercise of free will
            unhampered by the state.</p>
        <p>For the first time in this century, for the first time in perhaps all history, man does
            not have to invent a system by which to live. We don’t have to talk late into the night
            about which form of government is better. We don’t have to wrest justice from the kings.
            We only have to summon it from within ourselves. <value type="action">We must act on
                what we know</value>. I take as my guide the hope of a saint: <value type="unity">In
                crucial things, unity</value>; in important things, diversity; in all things,
            generosity.</p>
        <p><tone emotion="pride">America today is a proud, free nation, decent and civil, a place we
                cannot help but love. We know in our hearts, not loudly and proudly, but as a simple
                fact, that this country has meaning beyond what we see, and that our strength is a
                force for good</tone>. But have we changed as a nation even in our time? Are we
            enthralled with material things, less appreciative of the nobility of work and
            sacrifice?</p>
        <p><value type="humility">My friends, we are not the sum of our possessions. They are not
                the measure of our lives. In our hearts we know what matters</value>. We cannot hope
            only to leave our children a bigger car, a bigger bank account. We must hope to give
            them a sense of what it means to be a loyal friend, a loving parent, a citizen who
            leaves his home, his neighborhood and town better than he found it. <tone
                rhetoric="appeal_to_future">What do we want the men and women who work with us to
                say when we are no longer there</tone>? That we were more driven to succeed than
            anyone around us? Or that we stopped to ask if a sick child had gotten better, and
            stayed a moment there to trade a word of friendship?</p>
        <p>No President, no government, can teach us to remember what is best in what we are. But if
            the man you have chosen to lead this government can help make a difference; if he can
            celebrate the quieter, deeper successes that are made not of gold and silk, but of
            better hearts and finer souls; if he can do these things, then he must.</p>
        <p>America is never wholly herself unless she is engaged in high moral principle. We as a
            people have such a purpose today. It is to make kinder the face of the Nation and
            gentler the face of the world. My friends, we have work to do. <policy
                homelessness="general">There are the homeless, lost and roaming</policy>. <value
                type="equality">There are the children who have nothing, no love, no
                normalcy</value>. <policy health="addiction">There are those who cannot free
                themselves of enslavement to whatever addiction—drugs</policy>, <tone
                emotion="provoking">welfare, the demoralization that rules the slum</tone>. <policy
                crime="safety">There is crime to be conquered, the rough crime of the
                streets</policy>. <value type="security">There are young women to be helped who are
                about to become mothers of children they can’t care for and might not love. They
                need our care, our guidance</value>, and our education, <policy health="abortion"
                >though we bless them for choosing life</policy>.</p>
        <p>The old solution, <policy economy="general">the old way, was to think that public money
                alone could end these problems. But we have learned that is not so. And in any case,
                our funds are low. We have a deficit to bring down</policy>. We have more will than
            wallet; but will is what we need. We will make the hard choices, looking at what we have
            and perhaps allocating it differently, making our decisions based on honest need and
            prudent safety. And then we will do the wisest thing of all: <tone emotion="pride">We
                will turn to the only resource we have that in times of need always grows—the
                goodness and the courage of the American people</tone>.</p>
        <p>I am speaking of a new engagement in the lives of others, a new activism, hands-on and
            involved, that gets the job done. <value type="unity">We must bring in the generations,
                harnessing the unused talent of the elderly and the unfocused energy of the
                young</value>. For not only leadership is passed from generation to generation, but
            so is stewardship. And the generation born after the Second World War has come of
            age.</p>
        <p>I have spoken of a thousand points of light, of all the community organizations that are
            spread like stars throughout the Nation, doing good. We will work hand in hand,
            encouraging, sometimes leading, sometimes being led, rewarding. We will work on this in
            the White House, in the Cabinet agencies. I will go to the people and the programs that
            are the brighter points of light, and I will ask every member of my government to become
            involved. <value type="restoration">The old ideas are new again because they are not
                old, they are timeless: duty, sacrifice, commitment, and a patriotism that finds its
                expression in taking part and pitching in</value>.</p>
        <p>We need a new engagement, too, between the Executive and the Congress. The challenges
            before us will be thrashed out with the House and the Senate. We must bring the Federal
            budget into balance. <value type="unity">And we must ensure that America stands before
                the world united</value>, strong, <policy military="peace">at peace</policy>, <policy
                economy="general">and fiscally sound</policy>. But, of course, things may be
            difficult. <value type="unity">We need compromise; we have had dissension. We need
                harmony; we have had a chorus of discordant voices</value>.</p>
        <p>For Congress, too, has changed in our time. There has grown a certain divisiveness. We
            have seen the hard looks and heard the statements in which not each other’s ideas are
            challenged, but each other’s motives. <value type="unity">And our great parties have too
                often been far apart and untrusting of each other</value>. <tone
                rhetoric="appeal_to_past">It has been this way since Vietnam. That war cleaves us
                still</tone>. But, friends, that war began in earnest a quarter of a century ago;
            and surely the statute of limitations has been reached. This is a fact: The final lesson
            of Vietnam is that no great nation can long afford to be sundered by a memory. A new
            breeze is blowing, and the old bipartisanship must be made new again.</p>
        <p>To my friends—and yes, I do mean friends—in the loyal opposition—and yes, I mean loyal: I
            put out my hand. I am putting out my hand to you, Mr. Speaker. <value type="unity">I am
                putting out my hand to you, Mr. Majority Leader. For this is the thing: This is the
                age of the offered hand</value>. We can’t turn back clocks, and I don’t want to. But
            when our fathers were young, Mr. Speaker, our differences ended at the water’s edge. And
            we don’t wish to turn back time, but when our mothers were young, Mr. Majority Leader,
            the Congress and the Executive were capable of working together to produce a budget on
            which this nation could live. Let us negotiate soon and hard. But in the end, let us
            produce. <value type="action">The American people await action</value>. They didn’t send
            us here to bicker. They ask us to rise above the merely partisan. <value type="unity"
                >“In crucial things, unity”—and this, my friends, is crucial</value>.</p>
        <p><policy foreign="internationalism">To the world, too, we offer new engagement and a renewed
                vow</policy>: We will stay strong to protect the peace. The “offered hand” is a
            reluctant fist; but once made, strong, and can be used with great effect. <policy
                foreign="internationalism">There are today Americans who are held against their will in
                foreign lands, and Americans who are unaccounted for. Assistance can be shown here,
                and will be long remembered</policy>. Good will begets good will. Good faith can be
            a spiral that endlessly moves on.</p>
        <p>Great nations like great men must keep their word. When America says something, America
            means it, whether a treaty or an agreement or a vow made on marble steps. We will always
            try to speak clearly, for candor is a compliment, but subtlety, too, is good and has its
            place. <policy foreign="internationalism">While keeping our alliances and friendships around
                the world strong, ever strong, we will continue the new closeness with the Soviet
                Union, consistent both with our security and with progress</policy>. <tone
                emotion="optimistic">One might say that our new relationship in part reflects the
                triumph of hope and strength over experience. But hope is good, and so are strength
                and vigilance</tone>.</p>
        <p><tone emotion="triumph">Here today are tens of thousands of our citizens who feel the
                understandable satisfaction of those who have taken part in democracy and seen their
                hopes fulfilled</tone>. But my thoughts have been turning the past few days to those
            who would be watching at home, <value type="patriotism">to an older fellow who will
                throw a salute by himself when the flag goes by, and the women who will tell her
                sons the words of the battle hymns</value>. I don’t mean this to be sentimental.
                <value type="unity">I mean that on days like this, we remember that we are all part
                of a continuum, inescapably connected by the ties that bind</value>.</p>
        <p>Our children are watching in schools throughout our great land. <value type="democracy"
                >And to them I say, thank you for watching democracy’s big day. For democracy
                belongs to us all, and freedom is like a beautiful kite that can go higher and
                higher with the breeze</value>. And to all I say: <value type="equality">No matter
                what your circumstances or where you are, you are part of this day, you are part of
                the life of our great nation</value>.</p>
        <p><value type="equality">A President is neither prince nor pope, and I don’t seek a window
                on men’s souls. In fact, I yearn for a greater tolerance, an easy-goingness about
                each other’s attitudes and way of life</value>.</p>
        <p>There are few clear areas in which <value type="unity">we as a society must rise up
                united</value> and express our intolerance. <policy crime="drugs">The most obvious
                now is drugs. And when that first cocaine was smuggled in on a ship, it may as well
                have been a deadly bacteria, so much has it hurt the body, the soul of our country.
                And there is much to be done and to be said, but take my word for it: This scourge
                will stop</policy>.</p>
        <p><value type="action">And so, there is much to do; and tomorrow the work begins</value>.
                <tone emotion="optimistic">I do not mistrust the future; I do not fear what is
                ahead</tone>. For our problems are large, but our heart is larger. Our challenges
            are great, but our will is greater.And if our flaws are endless, <value type="religion"
                >God’s love is truly boundless</value>.</p>
        <p>Some see leadership as high drama, and the sound of trumpets calling, and sometimes it is
            that. But I see history as a book with many pages, and each day we fill a page with acts
            of hopefulness and meaning. The new breeze blows, a page turns, the story unfolds. And
            so today a chapter begins, a small and stately story of unity, diversity, and
            generosity—shared, and written, together.</p>
        <p>Thank you. <value type="religion">God bless you and God bless the United States of
                America</value>.</p>
    </body>
</speech>
