
<?xml-model href="../SchemaDraft.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<speech>
    <meta>
        <name>Bill Clinton</name>
        <den>Baptist</den>
        <class>lower</class>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <party>Democratic</party>
        <profession>Lawyer</profession>
        <term>2</term>
        <title>Address by Bill Clinton</title>
        <date>January 20, 1997</date>
    </meta>
    <body>
        <p>My fellow citizens:</p>
        <p>At this last Presidential inauguration of the 20th century, <tone
                rhetoric="appeal to future">let us lift our eyes toward the challenges that await us
                in the next century</tone>. <tone emotion="optimistic">It is our great good fortune
                that time and chance have put us not only at the edge of a new century in a new
                millennium, but on the edge of a bright new prospect in human affairs</tone>. A
            moment that will define our course and our character for decades to come. We must keep
            our old democracy forever young. <tone rhetoric="appeal_to_past">Guided by the ancient
                vision of a promised land</tone>, let us set our sights upon a land of new
            promise.</p>
        <p><tone rhetoric="appeal_to_past">The promise of America was born in the 18th century out
                of the bold conviction that we are all created equal. It was extended and preserved
                in the 19th century, when our Nation spread across the continent, saved the Union,
                and abolished the awful scourge of slavery</tone>.</p>
        <p><tone emotion="pride">Then, in turmoil and triumph, that promise exploded onto the world
                stage to make this the American century</tone>.</p>
        <p><tone emotion="triumph">And what a century it has been</tone>. <policy economy="industry"
                >America became the world’s mightiest industrial power</policy>, <policy
                foreign="internationalism">saved the world from tyranny in two world wars and a long
                cold war, and time and again reached out across the globe to millions who, like us,
                longed for the blessings of liberty</policy>.</p>
        <p>Along the way, Americans produced the great middle class and security in old age; <policy
                education="schools">built unrivaled centers of learning and opened public schools to
                all</policy>; <value type="science">split the atom and explored the heavens;
                invented the computer and the microchip</value>; and <policy
                civil_rights="race">deepened the wellspring of justice by making a
                revolution in civil rights for African Americans and all minorities, and extending
                the circle of citizenship, opportunity, and dignity to women</policy>.</p>
        <p>Now, for the third time, a new century is upon us, and another time to choose. We began
            the 19th century with a choice to spread our Nation from coast to coast. We began the
            20th century, with a choice to harness the Industrial Revolution to our values of free
            enterprise, conservation, and human decency. Those choices made all the difference. At
            the dawn of the 21st century, a free people must now choose to shape the forces of the
            Information Age and the global society, to unleash the limitless potential of all our
            people, and, yes, to form a more perfect union.</p>
        <p>When last we gathered, our march to this new future seemed less certain than it does
            today. We vowed then to set a clear course, to renew our Nation.</p>
        <p>In these 4 years, we have been <tone emotion="stress">touched by tragedy</tone>, <tone
                emotion="pride">exhilarated by challenge, strengthened by achievement. America
                stands alone as the world’s indispensable nation</tone>. <policy economy="general"
                >Once again, our economy is the strongest on Earth</policy>. Once again, we are
            building stronger families, thriving communities, <policy education="opportunities"
                >better educational opportunities</policy>, <policy environment="climate_change">a
                cleaner environment</policy>. Problems that once seemed destined to deepen, now bend
            to our efforts: <value type="security">our streets are safer</value> and <policy
                welfare="change">record numbers or our fellow citizens have moved from welfare to
                work</policy>.</p>
        <p>And once again, we have resolved for our time a great debate over the role of Government.
            Today we can declare: Government is not the problem; and Government is not the solution.
            We, the American people, we are the solution.</p>
        <p><tone rhetoric="appeal_to_past">Our Founders understood that well, and gave us a
                democracy strong enough to endure for centuries, flexible enough to face our common
                challenges and advance our common dreams in each new day</tone>.</p>
        <p><value type="progress">As times change, so Government must change. We need a new
                Government for a new century</value>, a government humble enough not to try to solve
            all our problems for us, but strong enough to give us the tools to solve our problems
            for ourselves. A Government that is smaller, lives within its means, and does more with
            less. Yet where it can stand up for our values and interests around the world, and where
            it can give Americans the power to make a real difference in their everyday lives,
            Government should do more, not less. The preeminent mission of our new Government is to
            give all Americans an opportunity—not a guarantee—but a real opportunity to build better
            lives.</p>
        <p>Beyond that, my fellow citizens, the future is up to us. Our Founders taught us that the
            preservation of our liberty and our Union depends upon responsible citizenship.</p>
        <p>And we need a new sense of responsibility for a new century. There is work to do, work
            that Government alone cannot do. <policy education="schools">Teaching children to
                read</policy>. <policy welfare="change">Hiring people off welfare rolls</policy>.
            Coming out from behind locked doors and shuttered windows to help <policy crime="drugs"
                >reclaim our streets from drugs and gangs and crime</policy>. Taking time out of our
            own lives to serve others.</p>
        <p><value type="unity">Each and every one of us, in our own way, must assume personal
                responsibility—not only for ourselves and our families, but for our neighbors and
                our Nation</value>.</p>
        <p>Our greatest responsibility is to <value type="unity">embrace a new spirit of community
                for a new century. For any one of us to succeed, we must succeed as one
                America</value>.</p>
        <p>The challenge of our past remains the challenge of our future: Will we be one nation, one
            people, with one common destiny—or not? Will we all come together, or come apart?</p>
        <p><policy civil_rights="race">The divide of race has been America’s constant
                curse</policy>. <policy immigration="general">And each new wave of immigrants gives
                new targets to old prejudices</policy>. <value type="equality">Prejudice and
                contempt, cloaked in the pretense of religious or political convictions, are no
                different</value>.</p>
        <p><tone emotion="stress">These forces have nearly destroyed our Nation in the past. They
                plague us still. They fuel the fanaticism of terror, and they torment the lives of
                millions in fractured nations all around the world</tone>.</p>
        <p>These obsessions cripple both those who hate and, of course, those who are hated, robbing
            both of what they might become. <tone emotion="optimistic">We cannot—we will not—succumb
                to the dark impulses that lurk in the far regions of the soul, everywhere. We shall
                overcome them</tone>.</p>
        <p><value type="unity">We shall replace them with the generous spirit of a people who feel
                at home with one another</value>.</p>
        <p><value type="equality">Our rich texture of racial, religious and political diversity will
                be a godsend in the 21st century</value>. <value type="unity">Great rewards will
                come to those who can live together, learn together, work together, forge new ties
                that bind together</value>.</p>
        <p>As this new era approaches, we can already see its broad outlines. Ten years ago, the
            Internet was the mystical province of physicists; today, it is a commonplace
            encyclopedia for millions of schoolchildren. <value type="science">Scientists now are
                decoding the blueprint of human life</value>. <policy health="public_health">Cures
                for our most feared illnesses seem close at hand</policy>.</p>
        <p><policy foreign="internationalism">The world is no longer divided into two hostile camps;
                instead, now we are building bonds with nations that once were our adversaries.
                Growing connections of commerce and culture give us a chance to lift the fortunes
                and spirits of people the world over</policy>. <tone emotion="optimistic">And for
                the very first time in all of history, more people on this planet live under
                democracy than dictatorship</tone>.</p>
        <p>My fellow Americans, as we look back at this remarkable century, we may ask, can we hope
            not just to follow, but even to surpass the achievements of the 20th century in America,
            and to avoid the awful bloodshed that stained its legacy? To that question, every
            American here and every American in our land today must answer a resounding “Yes.”</p>
        <p>This is the heart of our task: With a new vision of Government, a new sense of
            responsibility, a new spirit of community, we will sustain America’s journey. The
            promise we sought in a new land, we will find again in a land of new promise.</p>
        <p>In this new land, <policy education="schools">education will be every citizen’s most
                prized possession. Our schools will have the highest standards in the world,
                igniting the spark of possibility in the eyes of every girl and every boy, and the
                doors of higher education will be open to all. The knowledge and power of the
                information age will be within reach, not just of the few but of every classroom,
                every library, every child</policy>. Parents and children will have time not only to
            work, but to read and to play together, and the plans they make at their kitchen table
            will be those of a better home, a better job, a certain chance to go to college.</p>
        <p>Our streets will echo again with the laughter of our children, <value type="security"
                >because no one will try to shoot them or sell them drugs anymore</value>. <policy
                economy="jobs">Everyone who can work will work, with today’s permanent underclass
                part of tomorrow’s growing middle class</policy>. <policy health="public_health">New
                miracles of medicine at last will reach not only those who can claim care
                now</policy>, <value type="equality">but the children and hard-working families too
                long denied</value>.</p>
        <p><policy foreign="internationalism">We will stand mighty for peace and for freedom and
                maintain a strong defense against terror and destruction. Our children will sleep
                free from the threat of nuclear, chemical, or biological weapons</policy>. <policy
                economy="industry">Ports and airports, farms and factories will thrive with trade
                and innovation and ideas</policy>. <tone emotion="pride">And the world’s greatest
                democracy</tone> will <policy foreign="internationalism">lead a whole world of
                democracies</policy>.</p>
        <p>Our land of new promise will be a Nation that meets its obligations: <policy
                economy="budget">A Nation that balances its budget</policy>, but never loses the
            balance of its values.</p>
        <p>A nation where our <policy health="health_care">grandparents have secure retirement and
                health care</policy>, and <tone rhetoric="appeal_to_future">their grandchildren know
                we have made the reforms necessary to sustain those benefits for their time</tone>.
                <tone emotion="pride">A Nation that fortifies the world’s most productive
                economy</tone>, <policy environment="preservation">even as it protects the great
                natural bounty of our water, air, and majestic land</policy>.</p>
        <p>And in this land of new promise, we will have reformed our politics so that the voice of
            the people will always speak louder than the din of narrow interests, regaining the
            participation and deserving the trust of all Americans.</p>
        <p>Fellow citizens, let us build that America, a nation ever moving forward toward realizing
            the full potential of all its citizens. Prosperity and power, yes, they are important,
            and we must maintain them, <value type="progress">but let us never forget: The greatest
                progress we have made, and the greatest progress we have yet to make, is in the
                human heart</value>. In the end, all the world’s wealth and a thousand armies are no
            match for the strength and decency of the human spirit.</p>
        <p><tone rhetoric="appeal_to_past">Thirty-four years ago, the man whose life we celebrate
                today spoke to us down there, at the other end of this Mall, in words that moved the
                conscience of a Nation. Like a prophet of old, he told of his dream that one day
                America would rise up and treat all its citizens as equals before the law and in the
                heart. Martin Luther King’s dream was the American dream. His quest is our quest:
                the ceaseless striving to live out our true creed. Our history has been built on
                such dreams and labors, and by our dreams and labors, we will redeem the promise of
                America in the 21st century</tone>.</p>
        <p>To that effort, I pledge all my strength and every power of my office. I ask the Members
            of Congress here to join in that pledge. The American people returned to office a
            President of one party and a Congress of another. <value type="unity">Surely, they did
                not do this to advance the politics of petty bickering and extreme partisanship they
                plainly deplore</value>.</p>
        <p>No, they call on us all instead to be repairers of the breach and to move on with
            America’s mission.</p>
        <p><tone emotion="pride">America demands and deserves big things from us—and nothing big
                ever came from being small</tone>.</p>
        <p>Let us remember the <value type="religion">timeless wisdom of Cardinal Bernardin</value>
            when facing the end of his own life. He said, “It is wrong to waste the precious gift of
            time…on acrimony and division.”</p>
        <p>Fellow citizens, we must not waste the precious gift of this time, for all of us are on
            that same journey of our lives, and our journey, too, will come to an end. But the
            journey of our America must go on.</p>
        <p>And so, my fellow Americans, we must be strong, for there is much to dare. <tone
                emotion="stress">The demands of our time are great, and they are different</tone>.
            Let us meet them with faith and courage, with patience and a grateful, happy heart. Let
            us shape the hope of this day into the noblest chapter in our history. <value
                type="unity">Yes, let us build our bridge—a bridge wide enough and strong enough for
                every American to cross over to a blessed land of new promise</value>. <tone
                rhetoric="appeal_to_future">May those generations whose faces we cannot yet see,
                whose names we may never know, say of us here that we led our beloved land into a
                new century with the American dream alive for all her children</tone>, <value
                type="unity">with the American promise of a more perfect Union a reality for all her
                people</value>, <policy foreign="internationalism">with America’s bright flame of
                freedom spreading throughout all the world</policy>.</p>
        <p>From the height of this place and the summit of this century, let us go forth. <value
                type="religion">May God “strengthen our hands for the good work ahead”—and always,
                always bless our America</value>.</p>
    </body>
</speech>
