
<?xml-model href="../SchemaDraft.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<speech>
    <meta>
        <name>Lyndon Baines Johnson</name>
        <den>Disciple of Christ</den>
        <class>middle</class>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <party>Democratic</party>
        <profession>Teacher</profession>
        <term>2</term>
        <title>Address by Lyndon Baines Johnson</title>
        <date>January 20, 1965</date>
    </meta>
    <body>
        <p>My fellow countrymen, on this occasion, <value type="religion">the oath I have taken
                before you and before God</value> is not mine alone, but ours together. We are one
            nation and one people. Our fate as a nation and our future as a people rest not upon one
            citizen, but upon all citizens.</p>
        <p>This is the majesty and the meaning of this moment.</p>
        <p>For every generation, there is a destiny. For some, history decides. For this generation,
            the choice must be our own.</p>
        <p><value type="science">Even now, a rocket moves toward Mars</value>. <tone
                rhetoric="appeal_to_future">It reminds us that the world will not be the same for
                our children, or even for ourselves, in a short span of years. The next man to stand
                here will look out on a scene different from our own, because ours is a time of
                change—rapid and fantastic change bearing the secrets of nature, multiplying the
                nations, placing in uncertain hands new weapons for mastery and destruction, shaking
                old values, and uprooting old ways</tone>.</p>
        <p>Our destiny in the midst of change will rest on the unchanged character of our people,
            and on their faith.</p>

        <p>They came here—the exile and the stranger, brave but frightened—to find a place where a
            man could be his own man. <value type="democracy">They made a covenant with this land.
                Conceived in justice, written in liberty, bound in union</value>, it was meant one
            day to inspire the hopes of all mankind; and it binds us still. If we keep its terms, we
            shall flourish.</p>

        <p>First, justice was the promise that all who made the journey would share in the fruits of
            the land.</p>
        <p>In a land of great wealth, families must not live in hopeless poverty. <tone
                emotion="provoking">In a land rich in harvest, children just must not go hungry. In
                a land of healing miracles, neighbors must not suffer and die unattended. In a great
                land of learning and scholars, young people must be taught to read and
            write</tone>.</p>
        <p>For the more than 30 years that I have served this Nation, <tone emotion="stress">I have
                believed that this injustice to our people, this waste of our resources, was our
                real enemy. For 30 years or more, with the resources I have had, I have vigilantly
                fought against it. I have learned, and I know, that it will not surrender
                easily</tone>.</p>
        <p>But change has given us new weapons. Before this generation of Americans is finished,
            this enemy will not only retreat—it will be conquered.</p>
        <p>Justice requires us to remember that <policy civil_rights="race">when any citizen denies
                his fellow, saying, “His color is not mine,” or “His beliefs are strange and
                different,” in that moment he betrays America, though his forebears created this
                Nation</policy>.</p>

        <p><value type="liberty">Liberty was the second article of our covenant</value>. It was
            self-government. It was our Bill of Rights. But it was more. America would be a place
            where each man could be proud to be himself: stretching his talents, rejoicing in his
            work, important in the life of his neighbors and his nation.</p>
        <p>This has become more difficult in a world where change and growth seem to tower beyond
            the control and even the judgment of men. We must work to provide the knowledge and the
            surroundings which can enlarge the possibilities of every citizen.</p>
        <p><value type="liberty">The American covenant called on us to help show the way for the
                liberation of man. And that is today our goal</value>. Thus, if as a nation there is
            much outside our control, as a people no stranger is outside our hope.</p>
        <p><policy foreign="internationalism">Change has brought new meaning to that old mission. We
                can never again stand aside, prideful in isolation. Terrific dangers and troubles
                that we once called “foreign” now constantly live among us. If American lives must
                end, and American treasure be spilled, in countries we barely know, that is the
                price that change has demanded of conviction and of our enduring
            covenant</policy>.</p>
        <p><value type="science">Think of our world as it looks from the rocket that is heading
                toward Mars</value>. It is like a child’s globe, hanging in space, the continents
            stuck to its side like colored maps. We are all fellow passengers on a dot of earth. And
            each of us, in the span of time, has really only a moment among our companions.</p>
        <p><value type="unity">How incredible it is that in this fragile existence, we should hate
                and destroy one another</value>. There are possibilities enough for all who will
            abandon mastery over others to pursue mastery over nature. There is world enough for all
            to seek their happiness in their own way.</p>
        <p>Our Nation’s course is abundantly clear. We aspire to nothing that belongs to others.
                <value type="liberty">We seek no dominion over our fellow man, but man’s dominion
                over tyranny and misery</value>.</p>
        <p>But more is required. Men want to be a part of a common enterprise—a cause greater than
            themselves. Each of us must find a way to advance the purpose of the Nation, thus
            finding new purpose for ourselves. Without this, we shall become a nation of
            strangers.</p>

        <p>The third article was union. <value type="unity">To those who were small and few against
                the wilderness, the success of liberty demanded the strength of union</value>. Two
            centuries of change have made this true.</p>
        <p><value type="unity">No longer need capitalist and worker, farmer and clerk, city and
                countryside, struggle to divide our bounty. By working shoulder to shoulder,
                together we can increase the bounty of all. We have discovered that every child who
                learns, every man who finds work, every sick body that is made whole—like a candle
                added to an altar—brightens the hope of all the faithful</value>.</p>
        <p>So let us reject any among us who seek to reopen old wounds and to rekindle old hatreds.
            They stand in the way of a seeking nation.</p>
        <p><value type="unity">Let us now join reason to faith and action to experience, to
                transform our unity of interest into a unity of purpose. For the hour and the day
                and the time are here to achieve progress without strife, to achieve change without
                hatred</value>—not without difference of opinion, <tone rhetoric="appeal_to_future"
                >but without the deep and abiding divisions which scar the union for
                generations</tone>.</p>

        <p><tone emotion="pride">Under this covenant of justice, liberty, and union we have become a
                nation—prosperous, great, and mighty</tone>. <value type="liberty">And we have kept
                our freedom</value>. <value type="religion">But we have no promise from God that our
                greatness will endure. We have been allowed by Him to seek greatness with the sweat
                of our hands and the strength of our spirit</value>.</p>
        <p>I do not believe that the Great Society is the ordered, changeless, and sterile battalion
            of the ants. <value type="progress">It is the excitement of becoming—always becoming,
                trying, probing, falling, resting, and trying—but always trying and always
                gaining</value>.</p>
        <p><tone emotion="stress">In each generation, with toil and tears, we have had to earn our
                heritage again</tone>.</p>
        <p>If we fail now, we shall have forgotten in abundance what we learned in hardship: <value
                type="democracy">that democracy rests on faith</value>, <value type="liberty">that
                freedom asks more than it gives</value>, <value type="religion">and that the
                judgment of God is harshest on those who are most favored</value>.</p>
        <p>If we succeed, it will not be because of what we have, but it will be because of what we
            are; not because of what we own, but, rather because of what we believe.</p>
        <p>For we are a nation of believers. <value type="unity">Underneath the clamor of building
                and the rush of our day’s pursuits, we are believers in justice and liberty and
                union, and in our own Union</value>. <value type="liberty">We believe that every man
                must someday be free</value>. And we believe in ourselves.</p>
        <p>Our enemies have always made the same mistake. <tone emotion="pride">In my lifetime—in
                depression and in war—they have awaited our defeat. Each time, from the secret
                places of the American heart, came forth the faith they could not see or that they
                could not even imagine</tone>. <tone emotion="optimistic">It brought us victory. And
                it will again</tone>.</p>
        <p>For this is what America is all about. It is the uncrossed desert and the unclimbed
            ridge. It is the star that is not reached and the harvest sleeping in the unplowed
            ground. Is our world gone? We say “Farewell.” Is a new world coming? We welcome it—and
            we will bend it to the hopes of man.</p>
        <p>To these trusted public servants and to my family and those close friends of mine who
            have followed me down a long, winding road, and to all the people of this Union and the
            world, I will repeat today what I said on that sorrowful day in November 1963: “I will
            lead and I will do the best I can.”</p>
        <p>But you must look within your own hearts to the old promises and to the old dream. They
            will lead you best of all.</p>
        <p>For myself, I ask only, in the words of an ancient leader: “Give me now wisdom and
            knowledge, that I may go out and come in before this people: for who can judge this thy
            people, that is so great?”</p>
    </body>
</speech>
