<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../SchemaDraft.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<speech>
    <meta>
        <name>John F. Kennedy</name>
        <den>Roman Catholic</den>
        <class>upper</class>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <party>Democratic</party>
        <profession>Writer</profession>
        <profession>Sailor</profession>
        <term>1</term>
        <title>Address by John F. Kennedy</title>
        <date>January 20, 1961</date>
    </meta>
    <body>
        <p>Vice President Johnson, Mr. Speaker, Mr. Chief Justice, President Eisenhower, Vice
            President Nixon, President Truman, reverend clergy, fellow citizens, we observe today
            not a victory of party, but a <value type="liberty">celebration of freedom</value>—symbolizing an end, as well as a
            beginning—signifying renewal, as well as change. <value type="religion">For I have sworn before you and
                Almighty God</value> the same solemn oath <tone rhetoric="appeal_to _history">our forebears prescribed nearly a century and three
            quarters ago.</tone></p>
        <p>The world is very different now. For man holds in his mortal hands the power to abolish
            all forms of human poverty <policy military="nuclear_weapons">and all forms of human life.</policy> And yet the same revolutionary
            beliefs for which our forebears fought are still at issue around the globe—<value type="religion">the belief
            that the rights of man come not from the generosity of the state, but from the hand of
            God.</value></p>
        <p><tone rhetoric="appeal_to_history">We dare not forget today that we are the heirs of that first revolution.</tone> Let the word go
            forth from this time and place, to friend and foe alike, <tone emotion="proud">that the torch has been passed
            to a new generation of Americans—born in this century, tempered by war, disciplined by a
            hard and bitter peace, proud of our ancient heritage</tone>—and unwilling to witness or permit
            the slow undoing of those <value type="liberty">human rights</value> to which this Nation has always been committed,
            and to which we are committed today at home and around the world.</p>
        <p>Let every nation know, whether it wishes us well or ill, that we shall pay any price,
            bear any burden, meet any hardship, support any friend, oppose any foe, in order to
            <value type="liberty">assure the survival and the success of liberty.</value></p>
        <p>This much we pledge—and more.</p>
        <p><policy foreign="cooperation">To those old allies whose cultural and spiritual origins we share, we pledge the loyalty
            of faithful friends.</policy> <value type="unity">United, there is little we cannot do in a host of cooperative
                ventures.</value> Divided, there is little we can do—for we dare not meet a powerful challenge
            at odds and split asunder.</p>
        <p>To those new States whom we welcome to the ranks of the free, we pledge our word that one
            form of colonial control shall not have passed away merely to be replaced by a far more
            iron tyranny. We shall not always expect to find them supporting our view. <value type="liberty">But we shall
            always hope to find them strongly supporting their own freedom—and to remember that, in
            the past, those who foolishly sought power by riding the back of the tiger ended up
            inside.</value></p>
        <p>To those peoples in the huts and villages across the globe struggling to break the bonds
            of mass misery, we pledge our best efforts to help them help themselves, for whatever
            period is required—not because the <policy foreign="communism">Communists</policy> may be doing it, not because we seek their
            votes, but because it is right. <policy welfare="poverty">If a free society cannot help the many who are poor, it
                cannot save the few who are rich.</policy></p>
        <p><policy foreign="cooperation">To our sister republics south of our border, we offer a special pledge—to convert our
            good words into good deeds—in a new alliance for progress—</policy>to assist free men and free
            governments in casting off the chains of poverty. But this peaceful revolution of hope
            cannot become the prey of hostile powers. <tone emotion="stern">Let all our neighbors know that we shall join
            with them to oppose aggression or subversion anywhere in the Americas. And let every
            other power know that this Hemisphere intends to remain the master of its own house.</tone></p>
        <p><policy foreign="cooperation">To that world assembly of sovereign states, the United Nations, our last best hope in an
            age where the instruments of war have far outpaced the instruments of peace, we renew
            our pledge of support—</policy>to prevent it from becoming merely a forum for invective—to
            strengthen its shield of the new and the weak—and to enlarge the area in which its writ
            may run.</p>
        <p>Finally, to those nations who would make themselves our adversary, we offer not a pledge
            but a request: that both sides begin anew the quest for peace, <policy military="nuclear_weapons">before the dark powers of
            destruction unleashed by science engulf all humanity in planned or accidental
            self-destruction.</policy></p>
        <p><policy military="nuclear_weapons">We dare not tempt them with weakness. For only when our arms are sufficient beyond doubt
            can we be certain beyond doubt that they will never be employed.</policy></p>
        <p><policy military="nuclear_weapons">But neither can two great and powerful groups of nations take comfort from our present
            course—both sides overburdened by the cost of modern weapons, both rightly alarmed by
            the steady spread of the deadly atom, yet both racing to alter that uncertain balance of
            terror that stays the hand of mankind’s final war.</policy></p>
        <p><policy foreign="cooperation">So let us begin anew—remembering on both sides that civility is not a sign of weakness,
            and sincerity is always subject to proof. Let us never negotiate out of fear. But let us
            never fear to negotiate.</policy></p>
        <p><value type="unity">Let both sides explore what problems unite us instead of belaboring those problems which
            divide us.</value></p>
        <p>Let both sides, for the first time, <policy military="nuclear_weapons"></policy>formulate serious and precise proposals for the
            inspection and control of arms—and bring the absolute power to destroy other nations
            under the absolute control of all nations.</p>
        <p><tone emotion="inspiring">Let both sides seek to invoke the wonders of science instead of its terrors. Together let
            us explore the stars, conquer the deserts, eradicate disease, tap the ocean depths, and
            encourage the arts and commerce.</tone></p>
        <p>Let both sides unite <value type="religion">to heed in all corners of the earth the command of Isaiah—to “undo
            the heavy burdens…and to let the oppressed go free.”</value></p>
        <p><policy foreign="cooperation">And if a beachhead of cooperation may push back the jungle of suspicion, let both sides
            join in creating a new endeavor, not a new balance of power, but a new world of law,
            where the strong are just and the weak secure and the peace preserved.</policy></p>
        <p>All this will not be finished in the first 100 days. Nor will it be finished in the first
            1,000 days, nor in the life of this Administration, nor even perhaps in our lifetime on
            this planet. But let us begin.</p>
        <p>In your hands, my fellow citizens, more than in mine, will rest the final success or
            failure of our course. <tone rhetoric="appeal_to_history">Since this country was founded, each generation of Americans has
                been summoned</tone> to give testimony to its national loyalty. <value type="patriotism">The graves of young Americans
                    who answered the call to service surround the globe.</value></p>
        <p>Now the trumpet summons us again—not as a call to bear arms, though arms we need; not as
            a call to battle, though embattled we are—but a call to bear the burden of a long
            twilight struggle, year in and year out, “rejoicing in hope, patient in tribulation”—a
            struggle against the common enemies of man: tyranny, poverty, disease, and war
            itself.</p>
        <p><value type="unity">Can we forge against these enemies a grand and global alliance, North and South, East and
            West, that can assure a more fruitful life for all mankind?</value> Will you join in that
            historic effort?</p>
        <p><tone rhetoric="appeal_to_history">In the long history of the world, only a few generations</tone> have been granted the role of
            <value type="liberty">defending freedom in its hour of maximum danger.</value> <tone emotion="optimistic">I do not shank from this
                responsibility—I welcome it.</tone> I do not believe that any of us would exchange places with
            any other people or any other generation. The energy, the faith, the devotion which we
            bring to this endeavor will light our country and all who serve it—and the glow from
            that fire can truly light the world.</p>
        <p><value type="patriotism">And so, my fellow Americans: ask not what your country can do for you—ask what you can do
            for your country.</value></p>
        <p>My fellow citizens of the world: ask not what America will do for you, but what together
            we can do for the freedom of man.</p>
        <p>Finally, whether you are citizens of America or citizens of the world, ask of us the same
            high standards of strength and sacrifice which we ask of you. With a good conscience our
            only sure reward, with history the final judge of our deeds,<tone emotion="optimistic">let us go forth to lead the
            land we love, asking His blessing and His help, but knowing that here on earth God’s
            work must truly be our own.</tone></p>
    </body>
</speech>
