<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../SchemaDraft.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<speech>
    <meta>
        <name>Abraham Lincoln</name>
        <den>Unaffiliated</den>
        <class>lower</class>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <party>Republican</party>
        <profession>Lawyer</profession>
        <term>1</term>
        <title>Address by Abraham Lincoln</title>
        <date>March 4, 1865</date>
    </meta>

    <body>
        <p>Fellow-Countrymen:</p>

        <p>At this second appearing to take the oath of the Presidential office there is less
            occasion for an extended address than there was at the first. Then a statement somewhat
            in detail of a course to be pursued seemed fitting and proper. Now, at the expiration of
            four years, during which public declarations have been constantly called forth on every
            point and phase of the great contest which still absorbs the attention and engrosses the
            energies of the nation, little that is new could be presented. The progress of our arms,
            upon which all else chiefly depends, is as well known to the public as to myself, and it
            is, I trust, reasonably satisfactory and encouraging to all. With high hope for the
            future, no prediction in regard to it is ventured.</p>

        <p>On the occasion corresponding to this four years ago all thoughts were anxiously directed
            to an <policy military = "war">impending civil war</policy>. All dreaded it, all sought to avert it. While the inaugural
            address was being delivered from this place, devoted altogether to saving the Union
            without war, urgent agents were in the city seeking to destroy it without war—seeking to
            dissolve the Union and divide effects by negotiation. Both parties deprecated war, but
            one of them would make war rather than let the nation survive, and the other would
            accept war rather than let it perish, and the war came. </p>
        <p><policy civil_rights="slavery">One-eighth of the whole population were colored slaves</policy>, not distributed generally over
            the Union, but localized in the southern part of it. These slaves constituted a peculiar
            and powerful interest. All knew that this interest was somehow the cause of the war. To
            strengthen, perpetuate, and extend this interest was the object for which the insurgents
            would rend the Union even by war, while the Government claimed no right to do more than
            to restrict the territorial enlargement of it. Neither party expected for the war the
            magnitude or the duration which it has already attained. Neither anticipated that the
            cause of the conflict might cease with or even before the conflict itself should cease.
            Each looked for an easier triumph, and a result less fundamental and astounding.
             Both read the same Bible and pray to
                the same <value type="religion">God</value>, and each invokes <value type="religion"
                    >His</value> aid against the other.
           It may seem strange that any men should
                dare to ask a just <value type="religion">God’s</value> assistance in wringing their bread
                from the sweat of other men’s faces, but let us judge not, that we be not judged.
            The prayers of both could not be answered. That of neither has been answered
            fully. The <value type = "religion">Almighty</value> has <value type = "religion">His</value> own purposes.
            “Woe unto the world because of offenses; for it must needs be that offenses come, but
            woe to that man by whom the offense cometh.” </p>

        <p><policy civil_rights="slavery">If we shall suppose that American slavery
            is one of those offenses</policy> which, in the providence of <value type="religion">God</value>,
            must needs come, but which, having continued through <value type="religion">His</value>
            appointed time, <value type="religion">He</value> now wills to remove, and that <value type="religion">He</value> gives to both North and South this terrible war as the
                woe due to those by whom the offense came, shall we discern therein any departure
                from those divine attributes which the believers in a living <value type="religion"
                    >God</value> always ascribe to <value type="religion">Him</value>? Fondly
            do we hope, fervently do we pray, that this mighty scourge of war may speedily pass
            away. Yet, if <value type="religion">God</value>
                wills that it continue until all the wealth piled by the bondsman’s two hundred and
                fifty years of unrequited toil shall be sunk, and until every drop of blood drawn
                with the lash shall be paid by another drawn with the sword, as was said three
                thousand years ago, so still it must be said “the judgments of the <value type="religion">Lord</value> are true and righteous altogether.”</p>

        <p>
            With malice toward none, with charity for
            all, with firmness in the right as <value type="religion">God</value> gives us to see the
                right, <tone emotion="optimistic">let us strive on to finish the work we are in, to bind up the nation’s
                wounds, to care for him who shall have borne the battle and for his widow and his
                orphan, to do all which may achieve and cherish a just and lasting peace among
                ourselves and with all nations.</tone>
        </p>
    </body>
</speech>
