
<?xml-model href="../SchemaDraft.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<speech>
    <meta>
        <name>Barack Obama</name>
        <den>Unaffiliated</den>
        <class>lower</class>
        <state/>
        <party>Democratic</party>
        <profession>Professor</profession>
        <profession>Community Organizer</profession>
        <term>2</term>
        <title>Address by Barack Obama</title>
        <date>January 21, 2013</date>
    </meta>
    <body>
        <p>Vice President Biden, Mr. Chief Justice, Members of the U.S. Congress, distinguished
            guests, and fellow citizens, each time we gather to inaugurate a President, we bear
            witness to the enduring strength of our Constitution. <value type="democracy">We affirm
                the promise of our democracy</value>. <value type="equality">We recall that what
                binds this Nation together are not the colors of our skin or the tenets of our faith
                or the origins of our names</value>. <value type="patriotism">What makes us
                exceptional--what makes us American</value>--is our allegiance to an idea,
            articulated in a declaration made more than two centuries ago:</p>
        <p><tone rhetoric="appeal_to_past">We hold these truths to be self-evident</tone>,
                <value type="equality">that all men are created equal</value>, that they are endowed
            by their <value type="religion">Creator</value> with certain unalienable Rights, that
            among these are Life, Liberty and the pursuit of Happiness.</p>
        <p>Today we continue a never-ending journey to bridge the meaning of those words with the
            realities of our time, for history tells us that while these truths may be self-evident,
            they have never been self-executing; that while <value type="religion">freedom is a gift
                from God it must be secured by His people here on Earth</value>.</p>
        <p><tone rhetoric="appeal_to_past">The patriots of 1776 did not fight to replace the tyranny
                of a king with the privileges of a few or the rule of a mob</tone>. They gave to us
            a republic, a government of and by and for the people, entrusting each generation to
            keep safe our founding creed. For more than 200 years, we have. Through blood drawn by
            lash and blood drawn by sword, <value type="equality">we learned that no union founded
                on the principles of liberty and equality could survive half slave and half
                free</value>. <value type="progress">We made ourselves anew and vowed to move
                forward together</value>. <policy economy="commerce">Together, we determined that a
                modern economy requires railroads and highways to speed travel and
            commerce</policy>; <policy education="schools">schools and colleges to train our
                workers</policy>. Together, we discovered <policy economy="free_market">that a free
                market only thrives when there are rules to ensure competition and fair
                play</policy>. Together, we resolve that <value type="security">a great nation must
                care for the vulnerable and protect its people from life's worst hazards and
                misfortunes</value>. <value type="democracy">Through it all, we have never
                relinquished our skepticism of central authority, nor have we succumbed to the
                fiction that all society's ills can be cured through government alone</value>. Our
            celebration of initiative and enterprise, our insistence on hard work and personal
            responsibility, these are constants in our character.</p>
        <p><value type="progress">We have always understood that when times change, so must we; that
                fidelity to our founding principles requires new responses to new
            challenges</value>; that <value type="action">preserving our individual freedoms
                ultimately requires collective action</value>, for the American people can no more
            meet the demands of today's world by acting alone <value type="democracy">than American
                soldiers could have met the forces of fascism or communism with muskets and
                militias</value>. No single person can train all the <policy education="teachers"
                >math and science teachers we will need</policy> to <tone
                rhetoric="appeal_to_future">equip our children for the future</tone> or<policy
                economy="jobs"> build the roads and networks and research labs that will bring new
                jobs to our shores</policy>. Now, more than ever, we must do these things <value
                type="unity">together as one Nation and one people</value>.</p>
        <p><tone emotion="stress">This generation of Americans has been tested by crises that
                steeled our resolve and proved our resilience</tone>. <tone emotion="optimism">A
                decade of war is now ending</tone>.</p>
        <p><policy economy="recovery">An economic recovery has begun</policy>.</p>
        <p><tone emotion="pride">America's possibilities are limitless, for we possess all the
                qualities this world without boundaries demands: youth and drive, diversity and
                openness, an endless capacity for risk, and a gift for reinvention</tone>.</p>
        <p><tone emotion="optimistic">My fellow Americans, we are made for this moment</tone>,
                <value type="unity">and we will seize it so long as we seize it
            together</value>.</p>
        <p>For we, the People, understand that our country cannot succeed when a shrinking few do
            very well and a growing many barely make it.</p>
        <p>We believe America's prosperity must rest upon the broad shoulders of a rising middle
            class. <policy economy="jobs">We know America thrives when every person can find
                independence and pride in their work, when the wages of honest labor liberate
                families from the brink of hardship</policy>. <tone emotion="pride">We are true to
                our creed when a little girl born into the bleakest poverty knows she has the same
                chance to succeed as anybody else because she is an American</tone>, she is free,
                <value type="equality">and she is equal</value>, not just in <value type="religion"
                >the eyes of God</value> but also in our own.</p>
        <p><value type="progress">We understand outworn programs are inadequate to the needs of our
                time. We must harness new ideas in technology to remake our government</value>,
                <policy economy="tax">revamp our Tax Code</policy>, <policy education="schools"
                >reform our schools, and empower our citizens with the skills they need to work
                harder, learn more, and reach higher</policy>. But while the means will change, our
            purpose endures. A nation that rewards the effort and determination of every single
            American, that is what this moment requires. That is what will give real meaning to our
            creed.</p>
        <p>We, the people, <value type="equality">still believe that every citizen deserves a basic
                measure of security and dignity</value>. <policy health="health_care">We must make
                the hard choices to reduce the cost of health care and the size of our
                deficit</policy>. But we reject the belief that America must choose between caring
            for the generation that built this country and investing in the generation that will
            build its future.</p>
        <p>For we remember the lessons of our past, <tone emotion="provoking">when twilight years
                were spent in poverty and parents of a child with a disability had nowhere to
                turn</tone>. <value type="equality">We do not believe, in this country, freedom is
                reserved for the lucky or happiness for the few</value>. We recognize that no matter
            how responsibly we live our lives, any one of us, at any time, may face a job loss or a
            sudden illness or a home swept away in a terrible storm. <policy health="health_care"
                >The commitments we make to each other, through Medicare and Medicaid and Social
                Security</policy>, these things do not sap our Nation; they strengthen us.</p>
        <p>They do not make us a nation of takers; they free us to take the risks that make this
            country great.</p>
        <p>We, the people, still believe our obligations as Americans are not just to ourselves but
            to all posterity. <policy environment="climate_change">We will respond to the threat of
                climate change</policy>, knowing the <tone rhetoric="appeal_to_future">failure to do
                so would betray our children and future generations</tone>.</p>
        <p>Some may still deny the overwhelming judgment of science, but none can avoid the <policy
                environment="climate_change">devastating impact of raging fires and crippling
                drought and more powerful storms. The path toward sustainable energy sources will be
                long and sometimes difficult, but America cannot resist this transition; we must
                lead it</policy>. <policy economy="jobs">We cannot cede to other Nations the
                technology that will power new jobs and new industries; we must claim its promise.
                That is how we will maintain our economic vitality</policy> and our <policy
                environment="preservation">national treasure, our forests and waterways, our
                croplands and snow-capped peaks. That is how we will preserve our planet</policy>,
                <value type="religion">commanded to our care by God</value>. <tone
                rhetoric="appeal_to_past">That is what will lend meaning to the creed our Fathers
                once declared</tone>.</p>
        <p>We, the people, still believe that <policy military="war">enduring security and lasting
                peace do not require perpetual war. Our brave men and women in uniform, tempered by
                the flames of battle, are unmatched in skill and courage. Our citizens, seared by
                the memory of those we have lost, know too well the price that is paid for liberty.
                The knowledge of their sacrifice will keep us forever vigilant against those who
                would do us harm. But we are also heirs to those who won the peace and not just the
                war, who turned sworn enemies into the surest of friends, and we must carry those
                lessons into this time as well</policy>.</p>
        <p><policy foreign="alliance">We will defend our people and uphold our values through
                strength of arms and rule of law. We will show the courage to try and resolve our
                differences with other Nations peacefully, not because we are naive about the
                dangers we face but because engagement can more durably lift suspicion and
                fear</policy>.</p>
        <p><policy foreign="alliances">America will remain the anchor of strong alliances in every
                corner of the globe, and we will renew those institutions that extend our capacity
                to manage crisis abroad</policy>, for no one has a greater stake in a peaceful world
            than its <tone emotion="pride">most powerful Nation</tone>. <value type="democracy">We
                will support democracy from Asia to Africa, from the Americas to the Middle East,
                because our interests and our conscience compel us to act on behalf of those who
                long for freedom</value>. <value type="patriotism">We must be a source of
                hope</value> to the poor, the sick, the marginalized, the victims of prejudice, not
            out of mere charity but because <policy military="war">peace in our time</policy>
            requires the constant advance of those principles that our common creed describes:
            tolerance and opportunity, human dignity and justice.</p>
        <p>We, the people, declare today that the most evident of truths, <value type="equality"
                >that all of us are created equal</value>, <tone rhetoric="appeal_to_past">is the
                star that guides us still, just as it guided our forebears through Seneca Falls and
                Selma and Stonewall</tone>, just as it guided all those men and women, sung and
            unsung, who left footprints along this great Mall to <value type="religion">hear a
                preacher say we cannot walk alone</value>, to hear a ``King'' proclaim that our
            individual freedom is inextricably bound to the freedom of every soul on Earth.</p>
        <p>It is now our generation's task to <tone rhetoric="appeal_to_past">carry on what those
                pioneers began</tone>, <policy civil_rights="feminism">for our journey is not
                complete until our wives, our mothers, and daughters can earn a living equal to
                their efforts</policy>. <policy civil_rights="lgbt">Our journey is not complete
                until our gay brothers and sisters are treated like anyone else under the
                law</policy>, <value type="equality">for if we are truly created equal, then surely
                the love we commit to one another must be equal as well</value>.</p>
        <p><value type="democracy">Our journey is not complete until no citizen is forced to wait
                for hours to exercise the right to vote</value>. Our journey is not complete until
            we find a better way to <policy foreign="pro_immigration">welcome the striving,
                hopeful immigrants who still see America as a land of opportunity; until bright
                young students and engineers are enlisted in our workforce rather than expelled from
                our country</policy>.</p>
        <p>Our journey is not complete until all our children, from the streets of Detroit to the
            hills of Appalachia, to the quiet lanes of Newtown, <value type="security">know they are
                cared for and cherished and always safe from harm</value>. That is our generation's
                task--<value type="equality">to make these words, these rights, these values of life
                and liberty and the pursuit of happiness real for every American</value>.</p>
        <p>Being true to our founding documents does not require us to agree on every contour of
            life. It does not mean we will all define liberty in exactly the same way or follow the
            same precise path to happiness. Progress does not compel us to settle centuries-long
            debates about the role of government for all time, but it does require us to act in our
            time.</p>
        <p><tone emotion="stress">For now decisions are upon us, and we cannot afford delay</tone>.
            We cannot mistake absolutism for principle or substitute spectacle for politics or treat
            name-calling as reasoned debate. <value type="action">We must act, knowing our work will
                be imperfect. We must act</value>, knowing today's victories will be only partial
            and that <tone rhetoric="appeal_to_future">it will be up to those who stand here in 4
                years and 40 years and 400 years hence to advance the timeless spirit once conferred
                to us in a spare Philadelphia hall</tone>.</p>
        <p>My fellow Americans, the oath I have sworn before you today, similar to the one recited
            by others who serve in this Capitol, was an oath to <value type="religion">God</value>
            and country, not party or faction, and we must faithfully execute that pledge during the
            duration of our service. But the words I spoke today are not so different from the oath
            that is taken each time a <policy military="soldiers">soldier signs up for duty</policy>
            or <policy foreign="pro_immigration">an immigrant realizes her dream</policy>. My
            oath is not so different from the pledge we all make to the <tone emotion="pride">flag
                that waves above and that fills our hearts with pride</tone>. They are the words of
            citizens and they represent our greatest hope.</p>
        <p>You and I, as citizens, have the power to set this country's course. You and I, as
            citizens, have the obligation to shape the debates of our time, not only with the votes
            we cast but with the voices we lift in defense of our most ancient values and enduring
            ideals. Let each of us now embrace, with solemn duty and awesome joy, what is our
            lasting birthright. With common effort and common purpose, with passion and dedication,
            let us answer the call of history and carry into an uncertain future that precious light
            of freedom.</p>
        <p>Thank you. <value type="religion">God bless you, and may He forever bless these United
                States of America</value>.</p>
    </body>
</speech>
