
<?xml-model href="../SchemaDraft.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<speech>
    <meta>
        <name>Franklin D. Roosevelt</name>
        <den>Episcopal</den>
        <class>upper</class>
        <state>New York</state>
        <party>Democratic</party>
        <profession>Lawyer</profession>
        <term>3</term>
        <title>Address by Franklin D. Roosevelt</title>
        <date>January 20, 1945</date>
    </meta>
    <body>
        <p>Mr. Chief Justice, Mr. Vice President, my friends, you will understand and, I believe,
            agree with my wish that the form of this inauguration be simple and its words brief.</p>
        <p><tone emotion="stress">We Americans of today, together with our allies, are passing
                through a period of supreme test</tone>. <value type="democracy">It is a test of our
                courage—of our resolve—of our wisdom—our essential democracy</value>.</p>
        <p>If we meet that test—successfully and honorably—we shall perform a service of historic
            importance which men and women and children will honor throughout all time.</p>
        <p>As I stand here today, having taken the solemn oath of office in the presence of my
            fellow countrymen—<value type="religion">in the presence of our God</value>—<tone
                emotion="optimistic">I know that it is America’s purpose that we shall not
                fail</tone>.</p>
        <p><policy military="peace">In the days and in the years that are to come we shall work for
                a just and honorable peace, a durable peace, as today we work and fight for total
                victory in war</policy>.</p>
        <p><tone emotion="optimistic">We can and we will achieve such a peac</tone>e.</p>
        <p>We shall strive for perfection. We shall not achieve it immediately—but we still shall
            strive. <tone emotion="pride">We may make mistakes—but they must never be mistakes which
                result from faintness of heart or abandonment of moral principle</tone>.</p>
        <p>I remember that my old schoolmaster, Dr. Peabody, said, in days that seemed to us then to
            be secure and untroubled: “<tone emotion="stress">Things in life will not always run
                smoothly. Sometimes we will be rising toward the heights—then all will seem to
                reverse itself and start downward</tone>. <tone emotion="optimistic">The great fact
                to remember is that the trend of civilization itself is forever upward; that a line
                drawn through the middle of the peaks and the valleys of the centuries always has an
                upward trend</tone>.”</p>
        <p>Our Constitution of 1787 was not a perfect instrument; it is not perfect yet. <value
                type="unity">But it provided a firm base upon which all manner of men, of all races
                and colors and creeds, could build our solid structure of democracy</value>.</p>
        <p>And so today, in this year of war, 1945, we have learned lessons—at a fearful cost—and we
            shall profit by them.</p>
        <p><policy foreign="internationalism">We have learned that we cannot live alone, at peace;
                that our own well-being is dependent on the well-being of other nations far away. We
                have learned that we must live as men, not as ostriches, nor as dogs in the
                manger</policy>.</p>
        <p><policy foreign="internationalism">We have learned to be citizens of the world, members
                of the human community</policy>.</p>
        <p>We have learned the simple truth, as Emerson said, that “The only way to have a friend is
            to be one.”</p>
        <p>We can gain no lasting peace if we approach it with suspicion and mistrust or with fear.
            We can gain it only if we proceed with the understanding, the confidence, and the
            courage which flow from conviction.</p>
        <p><value type="religion">The Almighty God has blessed our land in many ways. He has given
                our people stout hearts and strong arms with which to strike mighty blows for
                freedom and truth. He has given to our country a faith which has become the hope of
                all peoples in an anguished world</value>.</p>
        <p><value type="religion">So we pray to Him now for the vision to see our way clearly—to see
                the way that leads to a better life for ourselves and for all our fellow men—to the
                achievement of His will to peace on earth.</value></p>
    </body>
</speech>
