<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../SchemaDraft.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<speech>
       <meta>
              <name>Harry S. Truman</name>
              <den>Baptist</den>
              <class>lower</class>
              <state>Missouri</state>
              <party>Democratic</party>
              <profession>Farmer</profession>
              <profession>Businessman</profession>
              <term>1</term>
              <title>Address by Harry S. Truman,</title>
              <date>January 20, 1949</date>
       </meta>

       <body>
              <p>Mr. Vice President, Mr. Chief Justice, and fellow citizens, I accept with humility
                     the honor which the American people have conferred upon me. I accept it with a
                     deep resolve to do all that I can for the welfare of this Nation and for the
                     peace of the world.</p>
              <p>In performing the duties of my office, I need the help and prayers of every one of
                     you. I ask for your encouragement and your support. <tone emotion="optimistic"
                            >The tasks we face are difficult, and we can accomplish them only if we
                            work together</tone>.</p>
              <p><tone emotion="stress">Each period of our national history has had its special
                            challenges. Those that confront us now are as momentous as any in the
                            past</tone>. Today marks the beginning not only of a new administration,
                     but of a period that will be eventful, perhaps decisive, for us and for the
                     world.</p>
              <p>It may be our lot to experience, and in large measure to bring about, a major
                     turning point in the long history of the human race. <tone emotion="stress">The
                            first half of this century has been marked by unprecedented and brutal
                            attacks on the rights of man, and by the two most frightful wars in
                            history</tone>. <policy military="peace">The supreme need of our time is
                            for men to learn to live together in peace and harmony</policy>.</p>
              <p><tone emotion="stress">The peoples of the earth face the future with grave
                            uncertainty, composed almost equally of great hopes and great
                            fears</tone>. In this time of doubt, they look to the United States as
                     never before for good will, strength, and wise leadership.</p>
              <p>It is fitting, therefore, that we take this occasion to proclaim to the world the
                     essential principles of the faith by which we live, and to declare our aims to
                     all peoples.</p>
              <p>The American people stand firm in the faith which has inspired this Nation from the
                     beginning. <value type="equality">We believe that all men have a right to equal
                            justice under law and equal opportunity to share in the common good. We
                            believe that all men have the right to freedom of thought and
                            expression</value>. <value type="religion">We believe that all men are
                            created equal because they are created in the image of God.</value></p>
              <p>From this faith we will not be moved.</p>
              <p><value type="liberty">The American people desire, and are determined to work for, a
                            world in which all nations and all peoples are free to govern themselves
                            as they see fit, and to achieve a decent and satisfying life</value>.
                            <policy military="peace">Above all else, our people desire, and are
                            determined to work for, peace on earth—a just and lasting peace—based on
                            genuine agreement freely arrived at by equals</policy>.</p>
              <p>In the pursuit of these aims, the United States and other like-minded nations find
                     themselves directly opposed by a regime with contrary aims and a totally
                     different concept of life.</p>
              <p><tone emotion="provoking">That regime adheres to a false philosophy which purports
                            to offer freedom, security, and greater opportunity to mankind. Misled
                            by this philosophy, many peoples have sacrificed their liberties only to
                            learn to their sorrow that deceit and mockery, poverty and tyranny, are
                            their reward</tone>.</p>
              <p>That false philosophy is communism.</p>
              <p><value type="democracy">Communism is based on the belief that man is so weak and
                            inadequate that he is unable to govern himself, and therefore requires
                            the rule of strong masters</value>.</p>
              <p><value type="democracy">>Democracy is based on the conviction that man has the
                            moral and intellectual capacity, as well as the inalienable right, to
                            govern himself with reason and justice</value>.</p>
              <p>Communism subjects the individual to arrest without lawful cause, punishment
                     without trial, and forced labor as the chattel of the state. It decrees what
                     information he shall receive, what art he shall produce, what leaders he shall
                     follow, and what thoughts he shall think.</p>
              <p><value type="democracy">Democracy maintains that government is established for the
                            benefit of the individual, and is charged with the responsibility of
                            protecting the rights of the individual and his freedom in the exercise
                            of his abilities</value>.</p>
              <p>Communism maintains that social wrongs can be corrected only by violence.</p>
              <p><value type="democracy">Democracy has proved that social justice can be achieved
                            through peaceful change</value>.</p>
              <p>Communism holds that the world is so deeply divided into opposing classes that war
                     is inevitable.</p>
              <p><value type="democracy">Democracy holds that free nations can settle differences
                            justly and maintain lasting peace</value>.</p>
              <p>These differences between communism and democracy do not concern the United States
                     alone.People everywhere are coming to realize that what is involved is material
                     well-being, human dignity, and <value type="religion">the right to believe in
                            and worship God</value>.</p>
              <p>I state these differences, not to draw issues of belief as such, but because the
                     actions resulting from the Communist philosophy are a threat to the efforts of
                     free nations to bring about world recovery and lasting peace.</p>
              <p><policy military="peace">Since the end of hostilities, the United States has
                            invested its substance and its energy in a great constructive effort to
                            restore peace, stability, and freedom to the world</policy>.</p>
              <p>We have sought no territory and we have imposed our will on none. We have asked for
                     no privileges we would not extend to others.</p>
              <p><policy foreign="internationalism">We have constantly and vigorously supported the
                            United Nations and related agencies as a means of applying democratic
                            principles to international relations. We have consistently advocated
                            and relied upon peaceful settlement of disputes among
                     nations</policy>.</p>
              <p><policy military="arms">We have made every effort to secure agreement on effective
                            international control of our most powerful weapon, and we have worked
                            steadily for the limitation and control of all armaments</policy>.</p>
              <p><policy foreign="internationalism">We have encouraged, by precept and example, the
                            expansion of world trade on a sound and fair basis</policy>.</p>
              <p>Almost a year ago, in company with 16 free nations of Europe, we launched the
                     greatest cooperative economic program in history. <value type="liberty">The
                            purpose of that unprecedented effort is to invigorate and strengthen
                            democracy in Europe, so that the free people of that continent can
                            resume their rightful place in the forefront of civilization and can
                            contribute once more to the security and welfare of the
                     world</value>.</p>
              <p><tone emotion="pride">Our efforts have brought new hope to all mankind. We have
                            beaten back despair and defeatism. We have saved a number of countries
                            from losing their liberty</tone>. Hundreds of millions of people all
                     over the world now agree with us, that we need not have war—that we can have
                     peace.</p>
              <p>The initiative is ours.</p>
              <p><policy foreign="internationalism">We are moving on with other nations to build an
                            even stronger structure of international order and justice. We shall
                            have as our partners countries which, no longer solely concerned with
                            the problem of national survival, are now working to improve the
                            standards of living of all their people</policy>. We are ready to
                     undertake new projects to strengthen the free world.</p>
              <p>In the coming years, our program for peace and freedom will emphasize four major
                     courses of action.</p>
              <p><policy foreign="internationalism">First, we will continue to give unfaltering
                            support to the United Nations and related agencies, and we will continue
                            to search for ways to strengthen their authority and increase their
                            effectiveness. We believe that the United Nations will be strengthened
                            by the new nations which are being formed in lands now advancing toward
                            self-government under democratic principles</policy>.</p>
              <p><policy economy="global_economy">Second, we will continue our programs for world
                            economic recovery</policy>.</p>
              <p>This means, first of all, that we must keep our full weight behind the European
                     recovery program. We are confident of the success of this major venture in
                     world recovery. We believe that our partners in this effort will achieve the
                     status of self-supporting nations once again.</p>
              <p><policy foreign="internationalism">In addition, we must carry out our plans for
                            reducing the barriers to world trade and increasing its volume. Economic
                            recovery and peace itself depend on increased world trade</policy>.</p>
              <p>Third, we will strengthen freedom-loving nations against the dangers of
                     aggression.</p>
              <p><policy foreign="internationalism">We are now working out with a number of
                            countries a joint agreement designed to strengthen the security of the
                            North Atlantic area. Such an agreement would take the form of a
                            collective defense arrangement within the terms of the United Nations
                            Charter</policy>.</p>
              <p><policy foreign="internationalism">We have already established such a defense pact
                            for the Western Hemisphere by the treaty of Rio de Janeiro</policy>.</p>
              <p><policy foreign="internationalism">The primary purpose of these agreements is to
                            provide unmistakable proof of the joint determination of the free
                            countries to resist armed attack from any quarter. Each country
                            participating in these arrangements must contribute all it can to the
                            common defense</policy>.</p>
              <p><value type="security">If we can make it sufficiently clear, in advance, that any
                            armed attack affecting our national security would be met with
                            overwhelming force, the armed attack might never occur</value>.</p>
              <p><policy foreign="internationalism">I hope soon to send to the Senate a treaty
                            respecting the North Atlantic security plan</policy>.</p>
              <p><policy military="peace security">In addition, we will provide military advice and
                            equipment to free nations which will cooperate with us in the
                            maintenance of peace and security</policy>.</p>
              <p><value type="science">Fourth, we must embark on a bold new program for making the
                            benefits of our scientific advances</value> and industrial progress
                     available for the improvement and growth of underdeveloped areas.</p>
              <p><tone emotion="provoking">More than half the people of the world are living in
                            conditions approaching misery. Their food is inadequate</tone>. They are
                     victims of disease. Their economic life is primitive and stagnant. Their
                     poverty is a handicap and a threat both to them and to more prosperous
                     areas.</p>
              <p><value type="science">For the first time in history, humanity possesses the
                            knowledge and the skill to relieve the suffering of these
                     people</value>.</p>
              <p><value type="science">The United States is pre-eminent among nations in the
                            development of industrial and scientific techniques. The material
                            resources which we can afford to use for the assistance of other peoples
                            are limited. But our imponderable resources in technical knowledge are
                            constantly growing and are inexhaustible</value>.</p>
              <p>I believe that we should make available to peace-loving peoples the benefits of our
                     store of technical knowledge in order to help them realize their aspirations
                     for a better life. And, in cooperation with other nations, we should foster
                     capital investment in areas needing development.</p>
              <p>Our aim should be to help the free peoples of the world, through their own efforts,
                     to produce more food, more clothing, more materials for housing, and more
                     mechanical power to lighten their burdens.</p>
              <p><policy foreign="internationalism">We invite other countries to pool their
                            technological resources in this undertaking. Their contributions will be
                            warmly welcomed. This should be a cooperative enterprise in which all
                            nations work together through the United Nations and its specialized
                            agencies wherever practicable. It must be a worldwide effort for the
                            achievement of peace, plenty, and freedom</policy>.</p>
              <p>With the cooperation of business, private capital, agriculture, and labor in this
                     country, this program can greatly increase the industrial activity in other
                     nations and can raise substantially their standards of living.</p>
              <p><policy economy="global_economy">Such new economic developments must be devised and
                            controlled to benefit the peoples of the areas in which they are
                            established</policy>. Guarantees to the investor must be balanced by
                     guarantees in the interest of the people whose resources and whose labor go
                     into these developments.</p>
              <p><value type="democracy">The old imperialism—exploitation for foreign profit—has no
                            place in our plans. What we envisage is a program of development based
                            on the concepts of democratic fair-dealing</value>.</p>
              <p><policy foreign="internationalism">All countries, including our own, will greatly
                            benefit from a constructive program for the better use of the world's
                            human and natural resources. Experience shows that our commerce with
                            other countries expands as they progress industrially and
                            economically</policy>.</p>
              <p><value type="science">Greater production is the key to prosperity and peace. And
                            the key to greater production is a wider and more vigorous application
                            of modern scientific and technical knowledge</value>.</p>
              <p>Only by helping the least fortunate of its members to help themselves can the human
                     family achieve the decent, satisfying life that is the right of all people.
                     56</p>
              <p><value type="democracy">Democracy alone can supply the vitalizing force to stir the
                            peoples of the world into triumphant action</value>, not only against
                     their human oppressors, but also against their ancient enemies—hunger, misery,
                     and despair.</p>
              <p>On the basis of these four major courses of action we hope to help create the
                     conditions that will lead eventually to personal freedom and happiness for all
                     mankind.</p>
              <p>If we are to be successful in carrying out these policies, it is clear that we must
                     have continued prosperity in this country and we must keep ourselves
                     strong.</p>
              <p><policy foreign="internationalism">Slowly but surely we are weaving a world fabric
                            of international security and growing prosperity</policy>.</p>
              <p>We are aided by all who wish to live in freedom from fear—even by those who live
                     today in fear under their own governments.</p>
              <p>We are aided by all who want relief from the lies of propaganda—who desire truth
                     and sincerity.</p>
              <p><value type="liberty">We are aided by all who desire self-government and a voice in
                            deciding their own affairs</value>.</p>
              <p>We are aided by all who long for economic security—for the security and abundance
                     that men in free societies can enjoy.</p>
              <p><value type="liberty">We are aided by all who desire freedom of speech, freedom of
                            religion, and freedom to live their own lives for useful
                     ends</value>.</p>
              <p>Our allies are the millions who hunger and thirst after righteousness.</p>
              <p>In due time, as our stability becomes manifest, as more and more nations come to
                     know the benefits of democracy and to participate in growing abundance, <tone
                            emotion="optimistic">I believe that those countries which now oppose us
                            will abandon their delusions and join with the free nations of the world
                            in a just settlement of international differences</tone>.</p>
              <p>Events have brought our American democracy to new influence and new
                     responsibilities. They will test our courage, our devotion to duty, and our
                     concept of liberty.</p>
              <p><value type="liberty">But I say to all men, what we have achieved in liberty, we
                            will surpass in greater liberty</value>.</p>
              <p><value type="religion">Steadfast in our faith in the Almighty, we will advance
                            toward a world where man's freedom is secure</value>.</p>
              <p>To that end we will devote our strength, our resources, and our firmness of
                     resolve. <value type="religion">With God's help, the future of mankind will be
                            assured in a world of justice, harmony, and peace</value>.</p>
       </body>
</speech>
