<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="submission-01.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<Chekhov1888Letter><date>(No date), 1888.</date>
<body>
<para1>
... You say that writers are God’s elect. I will not contradict you. Shtcheglov calls me the Potyomkin 
of literature, and so it is not for me to speak of the thorny path, of disappointments, and so on. I do not 
know whether I have ever suffered more than shoemakers, mathematicians, or railway guards do; I do not know 
who speaks through my lips—God or someone worse. I will allow myself to mention only one little drawback 
which I have experienced and you probably know from experience also. It is this. You and I are fond of 
ordinary people; but other people are fond of us because they think we are not ordinary. Me, for instance, 
they invite everywhere and regale me with food and drink like a general at a wedding. My sister is indignant 
that people on all sides invite her simply because she is a writer’s sister. No one wants to love the 
ordinary people in us. Hence it follows that if in the eyes of our friends we should appear to-morrow as 
ordinary mortals, they will leave off loving us, and will only pity us. And that is horrid. It is horrid, 
too, that they like the very things in us which we often dislike and despise in ourselves. It is horrid that 
I was right when I wrote the story “The First-Class Passenger,” in which an engineer and a professor talk 
about fame.
</para1>
    
<para2>
I am going away into the country. Hang them all! You have Feodosia. By the way, about Feodosia and the 
Tatars. The Tatars have been robbed of their land, but no one thinks of their welfare. There ought to be 
Tatar schools. Write and suggest that the money which is being spent on the sausage Dorpat University, 
where useless Germans are studying, should be devoted to schools for Tatars, who are of use to Russia. I 
would write about it myself, but I don’t know how to.
</para2>
</body>
</Chekhov1888Letter>