<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Wilde>
    <Title>Wilde's Writings on Trial</Title>
    <italics>In his cross-examination of Oscar Wilde, Defense Attorney Edward Carson asked Wilde
        about the meaning of two of his more controversial writings (the writings below). This
        literary part of the trial was far less incriminating than the witnesses Carson planned to
        produce, and suggests that Carson enjoyed toying with Wilde. For his part, Wilde did his
        best to turn the proceedings into a joke, often supplying flippant answers to Carson's
        questions. Still, Wilde's answers were often very revealing of his philosophy of life.
        Wilde's radical individualism, hedonism, and "camp" sensibility became apparent in his
        answers to Carson's questions about his writings.</italics>
    <subtitle>phrases and philosophies for the Use of the Young</subtitle>
    <p>
        <bullet>The first duty in life is to be as artifical as possible.</bullet>
        <bullet>What the second duty is no one has as yet discovered.</bullet>
        <bullet>Wickedness is a myth invented by good people to account for the curious
            attraciveness of others.</bullet>
        <bullet>If the poor only had profiles there would be no difficulty in solving the problem of
            poverty.</bullet>
        <bullet>Those who see any difference between soul and body have neither.</bullet>
        <bullet>A really well-made buttonhole is the only link between Art and Nature.</bullet>
        <bullet>Religions die when they are proved to be true. Science is the record of dead
            religions.</bullet>
        <bullet>The well-bred contradict other people. The wise contradict themselves.</bullet>
        <bullet>Nothing that actually occurs is of the smallest importance.</bullet>
        <bullet>Dullness is the coming of age of seriousness.</bullet>
        <bullet>In all unimportant matters, style, not sincerity is the essential.</bullet>
        <bullet>In all important matters, style, not sincerity is the essential.</bullet>
        <bullet>If one tells the truth, one is sure, sooner or later, to be found out.</bullet>
        <bullet>pleasure is the only thing one should live for. Nothing ages like
            happiness.</bullet>
        <bullet>It is only by not paying one's bills that one can hope to live in the memory of the
            commercial classes.</bullet>
        <bullet>No crime is vulgar, but all vulgarity is crime. Vulgarity is the conduct of
            others.</bullet>
        <bullet>Only the shallow know themselves.</bullet>
        <bullet>Time is a waste of money.</bullet>
        <bullet>One should always be a little improbable.</bullet>
        <bullet>There is a fatality about all good resolutions. They are invariably made too
            soon.</bullet>
        <bullet>The only way to atone for being occasionally a little overdressed is by being always
            absolutely over-educated.</bullet>
        <bullet>To be premature is to be perfect.</bullet>
        <bullet>Any preoccupation with ideas of what is right or wrong in conduct shows an arrested
            intellectual development.</bullet>
        <bullet>Ambition is the last refuge of the failure.</bullet>
        <bullet>A truth ceases to be true when more than one person believes in it.</bullet>
        <bullet>In examinations the foolish ask questions that the wise cannot answer.</bullet>
        <bullet>Greek dress was in its essence inartistic. Nothing should reveal the body but the
            body.</bullet>
        <bullet>One should either be a work of art, or wear a work of art.</bullet>
        <bullet>It is only the superficial qualities that last. Man's deeper nature is soon found
            out.</bullet>
        <bullet>Industry is the root of all ugliness.</bullet>
        <bullet>The ages live in history through their anachronisms.</bullet>
        <bullet>It is only the gods who taste of death. Apollo has passed away, but Hyacinth, whom
            men say he slew, lives on.</bullet>
        <bullet>Nero and Narcissus are always with us.</bullet>
        <bullet>The old believe everything: the middle-aged suspect everything: the young know
            everything.</bullet>
        <bullet>The condition of perfection is idleness: the aim of perfection is youth.</bullet>
        <bullet>Only the great masters of style ever succeed in being obscure.</bullet>
        <bullet>There is something tragic about the enormous number of young men there are in
            England at the present moment who start life with perfect profiles, and end by adopting
            some useful profession. </bullet>
        <bullet>To love oneself is the beginning of a life-long romance.</bullet>
    </p>
</Wilde>
