<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<letter>
    <heading>
        <addressee>TO HIS SISTER.</addressee>

        <addressee>FEODOSIA,</addressee>
        <date>July, 1888.</date>
    </heading>


    <p>... <s>The journey from <proploc loc="Ukr" type="city">Sumy</proploc> to <proploc loc="Ukr"
                type="city" commonspell="Kharkov">Harkov</proploc> is frightfully dull. Going from
                <proploc loc = "Ukr" type="city" commonspell="Kharkov">Harkov</proploc> to <proploc loc="Crimea" type="city"
                >Simferopol</proploc> <hyperbole>one might well die of boredom.</hyperbole></s>
        <s><proploc loc="Crimea" type="geo">The Crimean steppe</proploc> is depressing, monotonous,
            with no horizon, <simile>colourless like <literature>Ivanenko’s
                stories</literature></simile>, and <simile>on the whole rather like the
                tundra....</simile></s>
        <s>From <proploc loc="Crimea" type="city">Simferopol</proploc> mountains begin and, with
            them, beauty.</s>
        <s>Ravines, mountains, ravines, mountains, poplars stick out from the ravines, vineyards
            loom dark on the mountains--all this is bathed in moonlight, is new and wild, and sets
            one’s imagination working in harmony with <literature>Gogol’s “Terrible
                Vengeance.”</literature></s>
        <s> Particularly fantastic are the alternating precipices and tunnels when you see now
            depths full of moonlight and now complete sinister darkness.</s>
        <s>I reached <proploc loc = "Crimea" type="city">Sevastopol</proploc> at night.</s>
        <s>The town is beautiful in itself and beautiful because it stands by a marvellous sea.</s>
        <s>The best in the sea is its colour, and that one cannot describe.</s>
        <s><simile>It is like blue copperas.</simile></s>
        <s>As to steamers and sailing vessels, piers and harbours, what strikes one most of all is
            the poverty of the Russians.</s>
        <s><simile>Except the <foreignlang lang = "russian">“_popovkas_,”</foreignlang> which look like <proploc loc = "Russia" type = "city">Moscow</proploc>
                merchants’ wives,</simile> and two or three decent steamers, there is nothing to
            speak of in the bay.</s></p>
    <p>
        <s>... In the morning it was deadly dull.</s>
        <s>Heat, dust, thirst.... </s>
        <s>In the harbour there was a stench of ropes, and one caught glimpses of faces burnt
            brick-red, sounds of a pulley, of the splashing of dirty water, knocking, Tatar words,
            and all sorts of uninteresting nonsense.</s>
        <s>You go up to a steamer: men in rags, bathed in sweat and almost baked by the sun, dizzy,
            with tatters on their backs and shoulders, unload Portland cement; you stand and look at
            them and the whole scene becomes so remote, so alien, that one feels insufferably dull
            and uninterested.</s>
        <s>It is entertaining to get on board and set off, but it is rather a bore to sail and talk
            to a crowd of passengers consisting of elements all of which one knows by heart and is
            weary of already....</s>
        <s><proploc loc = "Crimea" type = "city">Yalta</proploc> is a mixture of something European that reminds one of the views of <proploc loc = "France" type = "city">Nice</proploc>, with
            something cheap and shoddy.</s>
        <s>The box-like hotels in which unhappy consumptives are pining, the impudent Tatar faces,
            the ladies’ bustles with their very undisguised expression of something very abominable,
            the faces of the idle rich, longing for cheap adventures, the smell of perfumery instead
            of the scent of the cedars and the sea, the miserable dirty pier, the melancholy lights
            far out at sea, the prattle of young ladies and gentlemen who have crowded here in order
            to admire nature of which they have no idea--all this taken together produces such a
            depressing effect and is so overwhelming that one begins to blame oneself for being
            biassed and unfair....</s>
        <s>At five o’clock in the morning I arrived at <proploc loc = "Crimea" type = "city">Feodosia</proploc>--a greyish-brown, dismal, and
            dull-looking little town.</s>
        <s>There is no grass, the trees are wretched, the soil is coarse and hopelessly poor.</s>
        <s>Everything is burnt up by the sun, and only the <antho>sea smiles</antho>--the sea which has nothing to
            do with wretched little towns or tourists.</s>
        <s>Sea bathing is so nice that when I got into the water I began to laugh for no reason at
            all....</s>
    </p>
</letter>
