<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<nobel_lecture><category>Nobel Lecture</category> by <author>Juan Manuel Santos</author>,
        <location>Oslo</location>, <date>10 December 2016</date>. <title>Peace in Colombia: From the
        Impossible to the Possible</title>
    
    <adressees>Your Majesties; Your Royal Highnesses; distinguished members of the Norwegian Nobel
        Committee; dear fellow citizens of Colombia; citizens of the world; ladies and
        gentlemen</adressees>
    
    , <body>
        <p>Six years ago, it was hard for we Colombians to imagine an
            end to a <war>war</war> that had lasted half a century. To the great majority of us, <thought type="dream"><peace>peace</peace> seemed
            an impossible dream</thought> – and for good reason. Very few of us – hardly anybody – could
            recall a <thought type="memory">memory of a country at <peace>peace</peace></thought>. </p>
        
        <p>Today, after six years of serious and often intense, difficult negotiations, I stand
            before you and the world and announce with deep humility and gratitude that the
            Colombian people, with assistance from our friends around the world, are turning <thought type="dream">the
            impossible into the possible</thought>.</p>
        
        <p>A <war>war</war> that has brought so much suffering and despair to communities all across our
            beautiful land has finally come to an end.</p>
        
        <p>Like life itself, <peace>peace</peace> is a process with many surprises. Just two months ago, people in
            Colombia and indeed in the whole world, were shocked to learn that, in a plebiscite
            called to ratify the <peace>peace</peace> agreement with the FARC guerrillas, there were slightly more
            "No" votes than "Yes" votes.</p>
        
        <p>This outcome was completely unexpected.</p>
        
        <p>A flame of <thought type="hope">hope had been lit in Cartagena</thought> a week earlier, when we signed the agreement in
            the presence of world leaders, and now that flame appeared to be suddenly snuffed
            out.</p>
        
        <p>Many of us in Colombia recalled a passage from <title type="book">One Hundred Years of Solitude</title>, the great
            masterpiece of our Nobel Prize laureate <author>Gabriel García Márquez</author>, which seemed to
            illustrate the moment we were living:</p>
        
        <p> <quote speaker="garcia_marquez">"It was as if God had decided to put to the test every capacity for surprise and was
            keeping the inhabitants of Macondo in a permanent alteration between excitement and
            disappointment, doubt and revelation, to such an extreme that no one knew for certain
            where the limits of reality lay."</quote> </p>
        
        <p>We felt that we ourselves were inhabitants of Macondo, a place that was not only magical
            but also contradictory.</p>
        
        <p>As Head of State, I sought to understand the significance of this unexpected setback and
            called at once for a broad national dialogue to seek unity and reconciliation.</p>
        
        <p>I was determined to turn this setback into a chance to develop the widest possible
            consensus for reaching a new agreement.</p>
        
        <p>I devoted myself to listening to the concerns and recommendations of those who had voted
            "No", of those who had voted "Yes", and of the majority who did not vote at all – with
            the aim of achieving a new and improved agreement, an agreement that all of Colombia
            could stand behind.</p>
        
        <p>Not even four days had passed after the surprising plebiscite when the Norwegian
            Committee announced an equally surprising award of the Nobel <peace>Peace</peace> Prize.</p>
        
        <p>I must confess to you that this news came as if it were a gift from heaven. At a time
            when our ship felt adrift, the Nobel Prize was the tailwind that helped us to reach our
            destination: the port of <peace>peace</peace>! </p>
        
        <p>Thank you; thank you very much for this vote of confidence and faith in the future of my
            country.</p>
        
        <p>Today, distinguished members of the Norwegian Nobel Committee, I come to tell you – and,
            through you, the international community – that we achieved our goal. We reached our
            port.</p>
        
        <p>Today, we have a new agreement for ending the armed conflict with the <guerilla>FARC</guerilla>, which
            incorporates the majority of the proposals we received.</p>
        
        <p>This new agreement was signed two weeks ago, and it was endorsed last week by our
            Congress, by an overwhelming majority, so that it can be incorporated into our laws. The
            long-awaited process of implementation has begun, with the invaluable support of the
            United Nations.</p>
        
        <p>With this new agreement, the oldest and last armed conflict in the Western Hemisphere has
            ended.</p>
        
        <p>This agreement – as set forth by Alfred Nobel in his will – marks the beginning of the
            dismantling of an army – this time, an irregular army – and its conversion into a legal
            political movement.</p>
        
        <p>With this agreement, we can say that the American continent – from Alaska to Patagonia –
            is a land in <peace>peace</peace>.</p>
        
        <p>And we can now ask the bold question: if <war>war</war> can come to an end in one hemisphere, why
            not one day in both hemispheres? Perhaps more than ever before, we can now dare to
            imagine a world without <war>war</war>. </p>
        
        <p><closing>The impossible is becoming possible.</closing></p>
    </body>
</nobel_lecture>

<!-- I thought it would be interesting to look at the frequency with which Nobel Prize Winner President Manuel Santos of Colombia
    would use two conflicting words regarding Peace, in this case, I chose to look at the words "War" and "Peace" -->
